Contact

selkaji@hotmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/dr-selvanmurugan-rn-dnp-mba-mhafache-7b26656 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

CMSRN

Wound Care

Chemotherapy

Languages

Tamil

Malayalam

Telugu

Certifications

Fellow of the American College of Healthcare Executives (FACHE) CMSRN

Dr. Selvan Murugan RN,DNP,MBA,MHA,FACHE

Regional Chief Nursing officer (Michigan Market) at Prime Healthcare

Northville, Michigan

Summary

23 yrs experience in Nursing and Leadership. Short term goal is to become an Executive Leader as CNO/COO at midsize hospital. Long term goal is to become a CEO of midsize hospital.

A personable, dedicated Registered Nurse/Nurse Manager/Nurse Director with 23 years' experience to lead nursing/ healthcare teams, deliver optimal patient care, and maximize patient/employee satisfaction. Promotes positive and respectful communication with patients, family members, medical colleagues, and managers while assessing and evaluating patient care in accordance with all policies/procedures. Combines advanced nursing skills with creative leadership to facilitate high levels of both patient and employee satisfaction.

Experience

Prime Healthcare

1 year 2 months

Regional Chief Nursing officer (Michigan Market)

March 2020 - Present (4 months)

Michigan, United States

Chief Nursing Officer
May 2019 - Present (1 year 2 months)

M

UHS

Chief Nursing Officer

December 2016 - May 2019 (2 years 6 months)

Laredo, Texas Area

Reporting to the CEO, with 18 direct reports with indirect report 385 FTEs.

Other responsibilities include daily clinical operative decision making,
executing corporate initiatives at the facility level, and enforcing high standard,
quality patient care while complying with all regulatory standards. Additionally,
serve as a member on all leadership committees, medical staff committees,
and PI committees.

Accomplishments/Outcomes/Achievements:

- Serve as the Co-Chair for the Patient Experience Project at the corporate level, developing tools, documents, and policies pertaining to HR and bedside shift reporting.
- Served on the committee that scripted the system-wide training video used to educate nursing and ancillary staff.
- Decreased ED inpatient admit time from 320 minutes to 50 minutes.
- Decreased discharge turnaround time from 5 hours to 140 minutes.
- Decreased bed turnaround time from 180 minutes to 50 minutes.
- Decreased agency staff from 24 to zero.
- Reduced overtime from 7% to 4.1%.
- Successful completion of TJC survey, CP, Trauma level 3, NICU level 3, CoC, and Stroke surveys.
- Hourly rounding score increased from 40% to 70%.
- HCAHPS scores: Maintained at 50th-75th percentile or above.
- Expansion projects: Added 8 ICU beds, 4000 SF cardiac/pulmonary rehab, 2nd free standing ED, and 4 additional ORs with new surgical service.
- Employee engagement survey: 3.75 out of 4 in overall ratings.
- Decreased employee turnover rate from 21% to 14.5% (2017), top in UHS. 18.5% in 2018.
- Designed the templates for an hourly rounding and bedside shift reporting process; worked collaboratively with other CNOs to finalize these tools.

Community Health Systems
Assistant Chief Nursing Officer (ACNO)
April 2015 - December 2016 (1 year 9 months)

Victoria, Texas Area

Nursing Officer Collaborated with management staff, middle management staff, and front line staff to lead service excellence in all aspects of patient care while supporting the missions, values, and goals of DeTar Healthcare System.

Served as Member of the Safety committee, culture of safety, volume committee, Core member of Hip program committee, Quality council, patient care committee, EOC committee, and LDI committee.

Equal responsibilities and shared responsibilities with CNO on daily basis.

Served as leader of "STOP sever sepsis" program at facility level.

Accomplishments: - early detection, physician involvement, new equipment, reducing cost of sepsis care, Mortality rate reduced from 2.3 to 1.87

Successfully implemented Kronos Scheduler system at facility level Member of task force to create "efficient Transfer center" and through put plan

New staffing plan for inpatient units – reduced employee turnover rate to 9.8% (YTD) from 28% (2015)

Successfully implemented 3 months (year end) staff/FTE reduction plan from October to December. Achievement: - 39 FTEs reduction and \$150,000 reduction in OT

Responsible for daily productivity management for all nursing departments

Part of the senior leadership team who reached EBDITA of \$49 Million in 2015

Provide leadership for Psych program at DeTar including Geriatric Mental
health, Intensive outpatient department, & Senior care outpatient clinic

Successful completion of 2 TJC Mid-cycle surveys and a full TJC Lab survey

HCA Gulf Coast Division
Nurse Director
January 2013 - April 2015 (2 years 4 months)
500 medical center blvd, webster, tx 77598

Collaborated with management to lead service excellence in all aspects of patient care while supporting the missions, values, and goals of Clearlake Regional Medical Center.

* Served as Member of the Core Measure Committee, Safety committee, Patient Experience committee, fall committee, TJC prep committee, wound care Committee, AMP committee, EM committee, Patient flow committee, and Med safety Committee which analyzed patient fall data and introduced initiatives to reduce incident numbers/improve patient safety.

Directly managed Two Nursing Departments (Med-Surg & Oncology) with 100+ FTEs Maintained good productivity and PLUS report for at least 8 consecutive quarters Fall rate dropped down by 30% from 2013 to 2014 Piloted and implemented many successful programs includes "Virtual Sitter Rooms", "New leadership Rounding", "Patient Safety Rounding", "New Fall program", "Patient Discharge scanning / Throughput", and "Hospitalist Unit" Employee Engagement Survey: Achieved high scores in leadership support and values to the employees.

ALOS decreased to 3.7 from 5.8

Clear Lake Regional Medical Center 4 years 10 months

Interim Nurse Director
December 2012 - January 2013 (2 months)

I was working as Interin Director for Cardiac-Medical Department with 75 FTEs. I was responsible for day to day operation, management at the same time leading to group for best possible quality patient care.

Nurse Manager April 2008 - December 2012 (4 years 9 months) Webster, TX

Collaborated with management to lead service excellence in all aspects of patient care while supporting the missions, values, and goals of Clearlake Regional Medical Center.

###* Served as Member of the Core Measure Committee, Safety committee, wound care Committee, and Med safety Committee which analyzed patient fall data and introduced initiatives to reduce incident numbers/improve patient safety.

Directly managed 70 FTEs HCAHPS scores maintained above average at HCA level and National level in last two quarters Maintained good productivity and PLUS report for at least 5 consecutive quarters Hand hygiene scores improved from 30% percent to 80%. Fall rate dropped down by 60% from 2011 to 2012 Successfully opened 36 bed Med-Tele unit to full capacity with in 4 months including hiring 40 FTEs Received recognition from HCA Corporate office for Facility Scheduler Excellence achievement

Tenet Healthcare RN COORDINATOR / CLINICAL MANAGER October 2006 - March 2008 (1 year 6 months)

Daily operation of 40 bedded PCU

Oversaw nursing and clinical services to support/enforce hospital governance in safety, quality, standards, and infection control.

* Implemented an Hourly Rounding System in which nurses systematically checked in on patients.

This initiative reduced patient falls, improved patient satisfaction, and allowed the nursing team a more focused, productive work environment.

* Educated nursing team on Heparin, Cardiac Drugs, EKG's, and Critical Values.

Handled all interviews, hiring practices, supervision, training, performance evaluations, corrective action plans, and terminations with diplomacy and in accordance with labor laws. Developed and maintained personnel work schedules/assignments of the nursing, clinical, and support staff.

Education

Capella University

DNP, Nursing Administration · (2016 - 2020)

Texas Woman's University

MHA, Health/Health Care Administration/Management · (2013 - 2015)

Grand Canyon University

MSN, Nursing Administration · (2007 - 2011)

Grand Canyon University

Master of Business Administration (MBA), Health/Health Care Administration/Management \cdot (2007 - 2011)

Tamil Nadu Doctor M.G.R. Medical University

BSN, Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse · (1993 - 1997)